Part 3. You will hear part of a discussion between two textile students about their
research into sustainable fashion. First, you have some time to look at questions 21 to 24.
Now listen carefully and answer questions 21 to 24.
Shall we go through our research for our sustainable fashion project?
Good idea. I think I've done enough reading now.
Me too. I've learnt such a lot about what sustainability actually means.
Same for me with ethical fashion. I didn't really appreciate the difference between
that and sustainable fashion before doing this research.
I know. Most people use these terms interchangeably, but in fact,
the difference is quite distinct when you think about it. Sustainable relates to the environment
and ethical relates more to the way workers or animals are treated.
I totally understand why people get confused though. There are so many other terms used,
like eco-friendly, which is actually quite meaningless.
And the way companies use these terms when describing their products doesn't help.
They're often deliberately vague, I think, and don't provide enough information about
how their products are made. Yes.
It was interesting to read about the debates surrounding wool production
and how ethical and sustainable that is. It's generally considered to be sustainable
because it's a natural product. And it also lasts a long time
and can be recycled. All very positive. But I wasn't convinced by the argument
that wool production is sustainable because it doesn't use many chemicals.
What about all the fungicides and insecticides used in sheep farming?
Good point. And I couldn't find any evidence for the claim about sheep farming being better
for the environment than cattle farming. No, they're both really bad.
I read different reports about how unethical it is to even shear sheep. Some people say it's cruel,
but as long as the sheep are kept in good condition, I can't see anything wrong with it.
Me neither.
Before you hear the rest of the discussion,
you have some time to look at questions 25 to 30.
Now listen and answer questions 25 to 30.
Shall we talk about some of the semi-synthetic new fabrics now?
Okay, let's do that.
Let's start with lyocell. I've been reading about that.
Yeah, that's the one produced from the pulp of eucalyptus trees, isn't it?
Yes. And what happens with that is really impressive.
Over 99% of dissolving agents used in the manufacturing process are used again.
Yeah. Now, there are a few semi-synthetic fabrics that I'd never heard of. Like cupro, for example.
Made from byproducts of the cotton industry to create a kind of vegan silk.
But I'm not sure how sustainable this really is,
as there are so many reports of pollution caused by the manufacturing process.
It doesn't compare favorably with all the other sustainable fabrics we've looked at, no.
Bamboo is one fabric we're all familiar with,
but I didn't know that it was only organic bamboo that's truly sustainable.
Me neither. Apparently, the manufacturing process for a significant proportion of bamboo
is chemically quite intensive, which obviously can be quite damaging.
Ecoviral is an example of a semi-synthetic fabric which is becoming really popular.
Probably because manufacturing causes 50% fewer emissions
and takes up half as much energy as conventional fabrics.
That saves production costs as well as being better for the environment.
That's true. I think demand for cork will continue to grow.
It works really well in vegan shoes and bags.
And it's the only fabric that's fundamentally sustainable.
The cork trees it comes from are renewable,
and the product itself is both recyclable and biodegradable, which is unique.
And the harvesting process is actually good for the trees.
There are no downsides to using this source at all.
Hemp is another really good sustainable fabric from a natural source.
Yes. Did you know that cloves made from hemp protect the wearer from the sun?
And it's also antibacterial.
No, I didn't. But I did read that it's quite hard to grow,
so perhaps that's why it's not as common as you'd think.
I'm sure that'll change. Then, there are...
That is the end of Part 3.
You now have 30 seconds to check your answers to Part 3.